⊠rishabh1@andrew.cmu.edu

RISHABH KUMAR

5530 Fifth Avenue, Pittsburgh, PA-15232 www.linkedin.com/in/rishabhkumar777

SUMMARY

Recent graduate from Carnegie Mellon University interested in meriting an enriching full -time/internship opportunity in the field of data science, machine learning and data analytics.

A proactive learner with relevant professional experience and an aptitude to adopt new technologies quickly.

EDUCATION

Carnegie Mellon University (CMU), Pittsburgh, PA

Aug 2017-Dec 2018

Masters in Chemical Engineering with specialization in Machine Learning and Data Science

Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS)-Pilani, India

Aug 2011-Jul 2016

Bachelors in Chemical Engineering; Masters in Biological Sciences

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, MATLAB, Java, C++, R, FORTRAN, SQL

Software: ALAMO, MS Office, SAS, Aspen, GAMS, Eclipse, COMSOL, Android Studio, Weka

SPECIALISED COURSEWORK

Machine Learning, Applied Data Science, Reinforcement Learning, Process Systems Engineering, Mathematical Modeling, Microbiology, Biochemistry and Bioinformatics

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer (Part-time), Prescouter Inc., PA

Aug 2018-Dec 2018

- Developed a Naive Bayes classifier to perform database (~1.6 million documents) search through lemmatization and countvectorizer approach
- Improved search speed by 20% after optimizing parameters through grid search with cross validation

Data Analyst, ZS Associates, India

Jul 2016-Aug 2017

- Enhanced sales by 5% using DCF financial model to optimize promotion strategy and sales tactics
- Formulated GTM strategy via sales force deployment analysis for 6 drugs (\$50 million+ rev. potential)
- Identified setbacks in marketing and promotional response for companies in the global healthcare sector by building multivariate regression models

Marketing Analyst Intern, Beckman Coulter, India

Jul 2015-Dec 2015

- Leveraged research insights and team inputs to design accurate and evidence-based forecasting models along with clear visualization of key data sets
- Promoted a newly developed assay, HPV Oncotect, through competitive analysis in South East Asia

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant, Centre for Advanced Process Decision Making, CMU, PA

Aug 2017–Dec 2018

Diagnosis of Breast Cancer through Machine Learning

- Built a classifier achieving 98% accuracy through optimization and error maximization sampling
- Engineered features to improve the correlation coefficient and sensitivity of the model through ALAMO

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Gradient Boosting: Healthcare Expenditure Model | Python

Jan 2018-May 2018

- Developed a healthcare expenditure model with gradient boosting classifier using MEPS data
- Optimized the model by applying feature reduction through principal component analysis

Neural Network: Image recognition | Python

Jan 2018-May 2018

- Built a custom neural network with one hidden layer for optical character recognition
- Obtained an accuracy of 80% on the MNIST dataset

LEADERSHIP & ACHIEVEMENTS

• 1st Prize, Hackauton, CMU

Apr 2018

• CHEMSA, Vice President, CMU

Jan 2018–Dec 2018

• Soccer Team, Captain, BITS Pilani

Aug 2013-Aug 2014